[Music]
this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at se - radio net SC radio
brings you relevant and detailed
discussions of software engineering
topics at least once a month
su radio was brought to you by I Triple
E software magazine online at computer
or / software OpenStack is an open
source cloud operating system John
Currier is a founder of OpenStack and
the CTO of automata fair as autonomic
Steve Technology Officer John is
responsible for driving the
organization's automation strategy with
more than 20 years of IT industry
leadership experience John was most
recently CTO of CenturyLink innovation
labs focusing on new and emerging cloud
technologies including multi-cloud
interoperability and DevOps previously
John was strategic and technology leader
at app fog and he led the development
and delivery of the first three releases
of Microsoft Exchange Server and he also
led R&D for the Rackspace cloud John
prior is a founder and board member of
OpenStack
John welcome to software engineering
radio well thanks for having me Jeff
what is OpenStack OpenStack is a it's as
you said it's an open source project
it's a cloud operating system originally
the idea behind OpenStack was to create
an open source infrastructure as a
service platform and you know as the
original founders were Rackspace and
NASA and the two original projects were
a compute project in a object storage
project of course since then you know in
the I guess the last six years the
numbers of projects and the scope of the
project has grown well beyond that
original vision to level set for some of
our listeners who may not know the term
what is infrastructure as a service yeah
so the way this think about
infrastructure as a service is instead
of going out and buying your own
computers finding a building getting a
lease
hooking up power and air conditioning
and running a data center you're
essentially leasing that from somebody
else right so while you can have
projects that are private infrastructure
as a service when we talk about ayahs or
infrastructure as a service
most people are referring to public
clouds like Amazon Azure or Google cloud
right so the the simple way of thinking
about it is I'm essentially renting
servers from somebody else so we have
these these cloud public clouds like
Amazon Google at Microsoft Azure for
example why do we need an open source
cloud operating system well that's
that's a great question and I guess the
question could be why do we need any
open source versions of proprietary
implementations and I would I would
argue that first of all it's just good
for the industry and the ecosystem but
in particularly around cloud cloud is is
very collaborative right it's a a coming
together of a lot of different companies
and organizations and the ability to
collaborate collaboratively build a
large project like this is is very
powerful very few companies in the world
could launch and sustain a project
that's as large as OpenStack is today
and I would argue that having the last I
saw there are over 30,000 members of the
OpenStack foundation contributing toward
the betterment of the software it is a
great thing so it is this open source
infrastructure as a service operating
system could you talk about an example
of a company that uses OpenStack today
so we perhaps have a prototypical use
case that we can maybe refer back to
during during this show if we need to
yeah they're you know several and when I
say several hundreds of companies that
are using OpenStack today in one
for more another a couple that are you
know kind of poster children I would say
one is on the commercial side is Walmart
Walmart is using OpenStack inside their
their data centers as they build out
their e-commerce systems
the other one is CERN the research
laboratory that does the the large-scale
collider over in Switzerland and for
anybody who's been to any of the recent
OpenStack designs some it's both of
these companies that have come forward
and and talked about their use cases and
demonstrated how they're doing
large-scale deployments of OpenStack are
these organizations are they run by
people that have so they have their own
servers and they run OpenStack on top of
it or are they leasing
cloud hosting that they put OpenStack on
it's a great question and the answer is
depending upon the organization they may
do either of those or both so the you
know kind of typical installation when
you think of OpenStack is an on-premises
cloud right so a private cloud if you
will so I have my own datacenter and I'm
probably in virtualized try site you
know over the last 10 years or so I
choose using VMware or other
virtualization technologies and I really
want to provide you know more service
more automation and more responsiveness
to my my customers my internal customers
so cloud really is an automation layer
over the top of virtualization alright
so it allows me to you know kind of
control on-demand spin up of resources
whether they be virtual machines storage
systems networks etc right so when you
think of OpenStack most people are
looking at the use case where it's used
inside of a data center now it can also
be and with no no changing kind of model
it can be managed by somebody else right
so if I was a
prai's and didn't want to run my own
data centers but I you know contracted
one of the managed hosting companies and
said you know please run my
infrastructure on my hardware networks
and and so on that OpenStack is also
appropriate in that case and then of
course there are some cloud service
providers that run OpenStack and are
essentially competing in the you know
the public cloud space against Amazon
Microsoft Google etc running an open
strat OpenStack so now we should get
into how OpenStack works we have a
higher level perspective for some of the
use cases and how its deployed at a high
level
you mentioned the term virtualization
what is virtualization
well back in the old days you used to
buy a computer and you would put an
operating system on it and then you
would run one or many applications on
that operating system about 15 years ago
or so this this idea of virtualizing the
servers which really grew out of you
know techniques that have been around
for a long time in the mainframe in mini
computer world was brought to you know
kind of PC level servers and the idea
behind virtualization is I can take it
you know a single computer I can put a
hypervisor on it and what the hypervisor
does is it abstracts the the underlying
hardware and then it presents the
ability to run multiple stacks of
software from the operating system up
independently so essentially I could
take my one physical computer and make
it look like two or four or eight
virtual computers and if I'm a user of
those computers they don't look any
different than if I was talking you know
talking to a box that I could physically
touch so what is the relationship in a
little more detail what is the
relationship between the hypervisor and
the hardware that it sits on top of yeah
so the the hypervisors is a layer
software that knows what the physical
hardware looks like he knows what he
gotta call it he know it knows what the
this is not a this is not a gender
normative okay so he or she knows what
the the hardware looks like underneath
wear whether it be CPU whether it be the
storage system whether it be the network
and then it essentially creates driver
level endpoints that can be accessed by
a variety of different virtual machines
okay and just to drive home this what
the hypervisor is a little more talk a
little more about the we talked about
that or you just refer to the
relationship between the hypervisor and
the hardware below it talk a little more
about the relationship between the
hypervisor and the virtual machines that
it manages yeah so so the I provide are
allowed you to spit up virtual machines
and those virtual machines look and act
just like physical machines you have
drivers virtualized drivers that provide
the same services that a physical
machine would would do in terms of
access to the CPUs data storage networks
and etcetera right so so it really is a
translation layer between this
virtualized environment and the physical
hardware and it arbitrates request from
the variety of different virtual
machines down to obviously the physical
Hardware perfect so now that we have an
idea of hypervisors virtual machines the
hardware that all this is sitting on top
of OpenStack takes a collection of
hypervisors that are spread across a
data center or across multiple data
centers and it turns this collection of
hypervisors into a shared pool of
resources why is this useful
well the way you described it was was
very good a cloud really is an
automation layer over virtual machines
right so if you take a look at the the
history of data centers in the
enterprise you know we started off you
know man
20 years ago with client-server
architectures and then about 15 years
ago we had kind of the rise of
virtualization and pretty much over the
last you know 10 years or so most
serious computation shops have
virtualized that didn't solve the
problem in terms of delivery to the
organization right so it's still you
know the processes that enterprises have
for let's say a developer requesting a
virtual machine or developer requesting
a group of machines was still back in
the submit a ticket have somebody go
into a console or a command-line create
the the resources send it you know you
know update the ticket send email back
and this could take you know several
days about ten years ago Amazon started
Amazon Web Services and you know the the
you know key service at the time was EC
to EC to essentially was an automated
way of getting virtual machines
instantly and this is this is very
revolutionary so I could take my credit
card I could swipe it right so the
obviously so they could charge me and
then immediately I could say I want ten
virtual machines I want them to have
this much memory this much disk go and
within three minutes or so those
machines would be up and running and I
could use them inside the enterprise
it's taking longer to get to that but
what OpenStack and what cloud software
does is it provides that level of
automation over the top of
virtualization so it's it's really a
manager and Orchestrator of virtual
machines and resources
okay so that's that's a great a great
description so yours I think to
reiterate what you just said with this
shared pool of resources you get a a big
this big pool and there is an interface
on top of it that allows the developer
to not really have to worry about what's
going on when the developer says I want
to spin up I want to spin up some some
amount of compute and I don't want to
have to worry about you know a lot of
this configuration beyond the the
minimum that I should have to worry
about as a developer I can just specify
what I want and this huge pool of
resources will figure out under the hood
what to give me an actuality and I will
get a virtualized perfect plate of
resources that I need yeah yeah that's
that's a really good way of looking at
it as a developer right I used to have
to if you go back to generations I used
to have to go buy a physical server
unbox it right plug it in put the
operating system on it put my tools on
it you know find a place under my desk
and then when we moved into the virtual
world all that got kind of got taking
care for me but it I still had a
one-to-one relationship with the virtual
machine with cloud I just asked for the
resources that I want and I don't care
if it's you know on machine 1 or machine
a thousand inside of the the data center
as a developer I just want access to the
resources and and so we've really
abstracted away the developer having to
care about a lot of the the provisioning
pieces and to put a finer point on this
the shared pool of hypervisors that is
managed by OpenStack these hypervisors
can be of different types they can be
Zen or KVM or VMware or Windows Server
but the user interacts with those
hypervisors through a
consistent interface of OpenStack why is
this advantageous because you in the
real world you don't necessarily have a
homogeneous set of of anything right you
may have you know physical computers
from a variety of different sources you
may have that you know the the original
provisioning may be different you may
actually have them on different types of
networks so the real world is messy and
what OpenStack does is it provides a
abstracted interface over the top of the
messiness and then manages the
complexity underneath it so that as a
developer or really as an operator or
sysadmin of the system I don't really
need to worry about that the system will
take care of it for me
do OpenStack users in practice do they
tend to have a heterogeneity of these
different server types like KVM and
VMware and Windows Server like all all
within the same cluster when a
hypervisor is sitting under this
consistent layer of OpenStack along with
other hypervisors are there any
particular specs that the hypervisor has
to adhere to like in terms of storage or
CPU or other characteristics it's a good
question I don't know if it's if it's
really relevant so yes there's probably
some minimum amount of things that you
have you have to have right but if you
take a look at you know kind of any of
the modern hypervisor virtualized
virtualization systems whether it be you
know VMware or hyper-v or you know
whatever it is they are all good enough
to be driven by OpenStack and and
OpenStack can also drive bare metal
boxes as well so within that a bare
metal box essentially is a box without a
hypervisor so to ask kind of an
absurdist question what would keep me
from running OpenStack across a huge
cluster of raspberry pies you you
absolutely could do that and if I was
gonna set that system up I would not put
a hypervisor on on the PI device because
it's so small but you essentially run
those as bare metal boxes but each of
those would be individually addressable
compute endpoints to the OpenStack
scheduler
hmmm that's really interesting so do you
think not to get too far off course do
you think we could have a future where I
have like a data center in my closet and
it's just like things that are the size
of a raspberry pie and I can run huge
MapReduce jobs on them absolutely and if
you if you're you know kind of paying
attention to the the hotness around
docker and containers right so it that's
really driving us helping to drive us
towards that future as well because with
containers they're much more lightweight
than virtual machines and you can get a
lot higher density inside any particular
configuration so if you if you know for
instance if we took a Raspberry Pi
device and we considered that a bare
metal box and then we stacked a whole
bunch of docker containers inside of it
think about that you know kind of
compute power you could have there and
then cluster them out underneath an
Orchestrator like OpenStack
yes so this is getting pretty far
removed from the nature of OpenStack
discussion but I've done a number of
interviews with people where I've I've
ended up asking the question like when
when you really start to containerize
your infrastructure and you you're using
docker to what degree do do we get like
what is the effect of the economies of
scale when we can containerize our
architecture with more modern
technologies whereas maybe five or ten
years ago we were doing virtualization
like do you have any I don't know
statistics or numerical projections for
how economical it actually is well I can
answer that I guess anecdotally right so
after I you know I ran the engineering
team at Rackspace and you know that's
where we we founded OpenStack with NASA
I then went to hewlett-packard and stood
up a public cloud based on OpenStack my
next gig was a company called app fog
which was a platform as a service
company based on cloud foundry and this
is you know yet another level of
abstraction where from for a developer
it's a it's a wonderful environment
right because you just worry about the
logic and the components that you want
in your application and then you push it
into the system and that all the
operational pieces get taken care for
you under the covers of any pass system
they're all containerized right so if
you take a look at open shift or Cloud
Foundry or you know what have you all of
these systems are running containerized
systems and app fog we were taking
virtual machines that we were running in
a variety of different public cloud
infrastructures like Amazon Rackspace HP
etc and we were slicing those virtual
machines up to run containers so you
could take an 8 gig virtual machine
and run you know eight to ten different
containers inside of that so so you get
much better economics you get much
better density right so if you have an
application that's 512 Meg you don't
need to take an entire 8 gig virtual
machine just to run that you could you
can stuff more applications into the
same space and and so what we're seeing
is is with with docker and containerized
systems it's really an inside-out
platform as a service so docker Inc
basically took the the containerized
system inside their path and they
separated it out and they you know made
a standalone put an API on top of it and
have done a lot of really good things
into in terms of collaborative
development for developers and
containers and then what we're doing is
is with these containerized systems
we're now having to rebuild all the
stuff that made passes operational like
monitoring systems and health checks and
and things like that so it's a it's a
really interesting world but the short
answer to your question is is that I
think that you're you know you're gonna
get five to ten X better utilization and
of course that means and requires that
our schedulers are more intelligent as
well hmm okay great so let's we'll get
into the discussion of schedulers a
little bit later but let's let let's
kind of zoom out to a little bit of a
higher level OpenStack has a set of
design tenants and the two main goals of
OpenStack are scalability and elasticity
and to somebody who doesn't have a whole
lot of experience with building
infrastructures of service software
scalability and elasticity these may
sound like the same thing so what is the
difference between scalability and
elasticity that's a great question right
so if you take the scaling question
first it really is the ability to get
resources on
and right so let's say I build an
application and I'm selling something
and you know you know I'm running and I
have a certain amount of traffic to it
and suddenly it's Christmastime right
and all the traffic to my website goes
up you know 10x you know I either have
to have over provisioned earlier to
account for the fact that now I have 10
times the amount of traffic or when that
traffic shows up I want to scale out
right so I want to add resources on
demand
so that's really what scaling is and and
the goal the tenets of OpenStack is to
be massively scalable right so a a
OpenStack system can run hundreds of
thousands of virtual machines in a
cluster elasticity really is is very
similar in that you know you want to be
able to grow your your resource pools
but you also want to be able to shrink
them right and this is actually a very
key part of cloud right so if it was
just add add add that would be one thing
you'll be interesting but the fact that
I can actually increase my resource pool
on demand and I can shrink it on demand
right and I can do scaling both up and
down is is really what what we mean when
we say it's elastic
another design tenets of OpenStack is
that any feature that limits the main
goals of the service which are
elasticity and scalability any any
example of a feature that limits those
main goals must be optional and I think
this is interesting like I think it's
actually really important to have these
these principles laid out because it's
such a massive open source project and
you need to have some sense of alignment
among the team the distributed team but
what is an example of a feature that had
to be made optional with in OpenStack
because it
potentially limited scalability or
elasticity uh if you take a look at the
original networking options that we had
right so we had you know kind of flat
networking and we had a variety of
different modes of networking that you
could choose that was you know
interesting but we're networking got
really interesting was when this
Software Defined Networking kind of came
came into being and really spearheaded
with in OpenStack by nice Sarah who were
you know they were later acquired by
VMware but you know so suddenly we had
two different networking systems right
and you need it as an operator or a
somebody who's actually going to deploy
OpenStack you kind of had to choose
between the two of them and if we as a
as a group had a policy of saying ok you
you must now use software-defined
networking versus versus the built-in
networking modules I think that would a
really adoption but the fact
that you could choose and they you know
they were optional components made it
much easier for adoption because people
could choose the the architecture and
the mode and the style of deployment
that that they were comfortable with
so everything in OpenStack should be
asynchronous according to the design
tenants why is a synchronicity so
important if you make make things
synchronous you have contention and you
give blockage and you your performance
goes down so it's all around it's all
about throughput it's all about being
able to create computing systems data
centers etc that you can put a service
level agreement on that's particularly
important for enterprise adoption where
you know the enterprise IT department is
making you an SLA promise to the
business you know
that there will be only so much downtime
that there's certain performance levels
that are that will be maintained etc
right so if in fact you have synchronous
places in your your architecture or your
workflows or your systems that's where
things are going to bog down and that's
where you kind of lose control so it
really is all about maintaining
performance uptime and scale OpenStack
also emphasizes the importance of a
shared nothing architecture and to
somebody who doesn't really understand
this term it might sound kind of strange
like if you have an architecture where
nothing can be shared how do you convey
information from one piece of the
architecture to another so maybe you
could define the term shared nothing
architecture yeah so if I have a shared
architecture you know I may be using a
chunk of memory or a chunk of disk to
maintain state and this gets very you
know kind of problematic when you have
virtual machines that are what are
called ephemeral right so a virtual
machine can disappear on you it can go
away at any time so you have to
architect your system such that it's
okay if virtual machines go away if in
fact you're using shared state and you
you know you're dependent upon you know
this virtual machine to maintain its
view of the world and it goes away
that's a problem the way you get around
this is you use things like message
buses right so everybody's communicating
on a message bus you can subscribe to
certain events so you see you know state
changes and things like that
you have here each of each virtual
machine has its own view of the world
and it operates on that view independent
of everybody else's view could you give
an example of like hypothetically if
OpenStack would have been
foolishly a design in a way that shared
state was easy to do
why would shared state be dangerous what
is what is an example of maybe an
application-level bug that could
propagate from a situation with shared
state so it if we're if you're if we're
sharing state right I am dependent upon
the thing that's maintaining the state
to be correct right so let's say I'll
give you a good example when I first
went to Rackspace to do the cloud
engineering work they had a computing
infrastructure based upon a company that
they had acquired called slicehost and
they had built an object storage system
internally right when they you know and
then before my time but when they went
to launch the object system in the first
week it took a lot of traffic and it
went down and it took them several days
to bring it back the problem in the
design of that object storage system was
they had put a centralized database
right so you know as your storage system
you know you've got you know many many
many many disk drives and if you're
routing all your traffic and it's a
requirement that you do a synchronous
call to a database for each transaction
you can see how your scale is going to
be impacted the more people that are
trying to talk to the system the more
contention you're going to have on that
shared resource and the worse off you're
going to be which which we found to our
chagrin now the good news is is that we
learned our lesson from that rebuilt
from scratch the object storage system
and that's the system called Swift
that's in OpenStack today
okay great let's talk about eventual
consistency OpenStack is designed with
eventual consistency in the mind could
you define the term eventual consistency
and describe why that term is relevant
to OpenStack yeah absolutely it's it's
absolutely a key concept for large-scale
distributed systems right so the the
idea behind this is is that if you have
a lot of of systems I'll take these
storage system again as an example so
let's say I build out my storage system
and I've got ten thousand disk drives
right and the way that object storage
systems work in you know some instances
is by doing redundant copies right so I
writes a piece of data and he actually
gets splatted across the ten thousand
drives and there's at least three copies
right so if any time a drive goes a way
I know I've got two other good copies
that I can kind of kind of recover that
from now the idea though is is that we
have latency Zin systems and we have
delays in systems right and so if I've
got a program that's looking at a
particular bit of storage and I've got
another program that might be
geographically dispersed but on the
other side of a replication topology in
the storage system at any point in time
they both think they're looking at file
foo but foo for some amount of time
before the replication occurs is not the
same on both sides right so and that's
okay and that's what that's the the
whole idea behind the eventual
consistency eventually all everything
will come back and be consistent as the
replication works but we have to accept
the fact that in some time windows you
know a programming and program B will
get different results
querying what they think is the say
storage object and OpenStack has some
degree of tunable consistency also could
you also explain that term and explain
how the consist the level of consistency
with an open stack can be tuned yeah
this is something that actually that was
added after my time but the tighter that
you bring the consistency requirements
right you know essentially what you're
you know you're trading off resiliency
right so you could actually make a
system that is entirely consistent right
so so you know if we take eventual
consistency on one end and always
consistent on the other you can build
systems that operate in either of those
modes right with with OpenStack the
original design parameters for some
people were not adequate right and this
is a great thing about open source so as
part of the the the project the folks
that said you know what I don't
necessarily need this many copies but I
need them to be a tighter sink right I
need my those two programs that think
they're looking at the same source
object to all you know always get the
same answer if they ask the same
question that was added in as a normal
part of the open source development
process so now that we're talking about
open source could you give me an idea of
how the open source community of
OpenStack works and how people
collaborate with each other how the open
source progress progresses yeah I I love
this topic I think that open source you
know is is a tremendous movement I think
that a lot of the innovation in how we
collaboratively built software has come
from projects like OpenStack and
actually the the requirements that you
know large communities of folks that are
spread across many countries and
cultures
across many different time zones all
collaborating on you know a single
project has forced a lot of innovation
to happen and I'm seeing the results of
that innovation come back into things
like how enterprises are building
software how they're building their
continuous delivery pipelines how they
integrate automation into that you know
continuous integration continuous
delivery pipeline so with OpenStack we
started with a base set of tooling you
know around version control and code
reviews and test automation right and
over the years this has gotten very very
sophisticated so so that you know you
have your continuous integration piece
you've got your continuous testing piece
you got your continuous deployment
pieces and the tooling around that has
has actually grown up a lot of other
open-source projects like Jenkins as
well the original team that was building
you know kind of the tools for how we
managed our source code how we built it
how he did continuous delivery work for
me at Rackspace also work for me at
Hewlett Packard and those guys did a
tremendous tremendous job for the
open-source community and and through
that kind of collaborative effort that's
how a project like like OpenStack can
actually be as effective as it is it's
got a a good set of tooling a good set
of processes everybody knows what the
rules are if you don't play by the rules
right then you know you you just can't
affect the community the community says
you know no thank you we don't want
people that don't play by the rules and
then there's a very high level of
communication and the ability to get
your voice heard right so these are not
static you know written on the tablets
come down from the mountain
processes this is a living breathing or
you know organic process that's always
being reviewed anybody can make
suggestions anybody can you know join
the conversation and I think it makes
better software and speaking of
processes that make better software
testing is very important to OpenStack
development tell me about how testing
occurs what the best practices are for
you know some open-source committer who
needs to commit he wants to commit
something and he has to commit tests
associated with it and and maybe some of
the challenges that are associated with
testing a big distributed system like
OpenStack yeah that's a great topic
you know you as you manage it you have
to start off with a policy and a process
set of rules that says when you check in
code you check in test with it right so
that's that's just you know kind of you
will not pass a code review if you don't
have tests how you can actually validate
is a much more interesting question and
in some ways the distributed continuous
integration process really helps here
right so you can actually set up a mesh
and this is how the original Jenkins
system was set up for OpenStack where
you know you kind of have a master but
then you've got you know the slave CI
systems that could be tuned for
particular scenarios right so for
instance at Hewlett Packard when we were
standing up OpenStack we had a
particular data center topology right we
you know we obviously were using HP gear
HP networks HP racks etc so the what our
topology looked like was not the same as
anybody else's in the world and so we
you wanted to it was in our own best
interest to set up a slave integration
server so that with each check-in that
came into trunk for OpenStack it kicked
off the continuously gate integration
process you know would go through like
the basic unit test but then it would
also then farm out the work to the slave
CI servers including ourselves and we
would run through our you know the
testing on our particular configuration
and then we would be able to tell you
know we essentially gave a boat back to
the CI server say yay or nay right and
then of course it's up to it it's a
policy decision whether or not you know
if you have you know certain slaves
failing whether or not that blocks you
know the the merchant trunk or not but
but that's very effective and it also
works really well inside enterprises
that might have different business units
or departments or such we used it within
hewlett-packard to actually stitch
together you know like the networking
group and the software group and the
storage group each of those had their
own view of what was necessary to pass
in in the OpenStack components that they
were worried about and so we see a you
know a set of different CI servers that
they would would vote back and and
passed the information upstream okay
we've been talking about the development
of OpenStack itself and since we're
drawing to the end of the conversation I
do want to zoom out a little bit more
and talk about the usage of OpenStack so
with open Stax abstraction of a shared
pool of resources the developer gets
this set of api's exposed that gives the
user gives the developer access to
compute and networking and storage and
I'd love to discuss in more detail what
the experience is like for the developer
once these set of AP is the set of API
is exposed and and how can we leverage
these api's to build our systems well
you know that's that's that's the whole
point of this right the point of
OpenStack isn't to build a system to be
building the system although sometimes I
I think we lose sight of that when
you're inside the project the point of
the system is to actually create an
environment so that people can write
applications right and so you know the
api's that you're talking about the get
exposed they'd be you know even the the
platform services that get exposed are
all part of the you know kind of the the
tapestry that a developer will will look
at right so at the end of the day that
the point around cloud and cloud
deployments and and platform as a
service is all around making that
developer experience more seamless and
and really allow the developer to worry
about the logic of his of his system
rather than you know gee have I set up
the web server correctly or you know I
you know what are the the credentials
for the database that those sorts of
things
okay and perhaps we should there's one
more technical topic that we haven't
really dove into we said we mentioned
earlier is the scheduler what is the
scheduler and why is this relevant to
the topic of OpenStack so the scheduler
is really the heart of OpenStack it's
the heart of any kind of distributed
system whether you're talking about grid
or high-performance computing systems
whether you're talking about
containerized systems with schedulers
like kubernetes or mais O's what the
scheduler is is it it's a it's an
Orchestrator that says hey I've been
asked to deploy a certain workload where
should i where should I put it right and
to some degree is you know kind of like
am I going to deploy one instance and
like a deploy multiple instances and if
I deployed multiple instances what are
the rules for affinity and and a non
affinity and things like that but it it
really is the heart of the the compute
infrastructure the scheduler is is the
thing that says here's the request for
running this particular program where am
I going to put it in the fabric and you
know typically there'll be a feedback
loop there'll be a monitoring loop or at
you know call it a health check or
whatever you want to call it so that if
in fact you know I've deployed as a
scheduler I deployed this particular
workload I'll know if it's in trouble if
it's died and then typically within
cloud systems all of the infrastructure
is is what's called immutable so instead
of trying to fix something that's broken
we'll just you know shoot it in the head
and deploy another one and that remember
earlier we talked about the fact that we
can't count on virtual machines they are
ephemeral you can't count on them being
there
all the time and part of the reason is
this right if if in fact we have to take
this one out and put another one in its
place and you know hook it up to a load
balancer we will do that the other kind
of scenario that that comes into play
here is workload motion so for instance
if I have a particular server and I need
to bring that server down the first
thing I have to do is evacuate all the
virtual machines and all the
applications that are running on that to
other parts of the system and what will
happen is is that the notification will
come back to the scheduler saying hey
I've got you know 27 instances of
applications running here that you need
to find another home for and then the
scheduler will reschedule those and
which allows us then to basically shut
down the virtual machines and
applications on the server that's that's
going down for maintenance or whatever
so I'd love to close by kind of zooming
out further and projecting towards the
future you know we've got all these
different ways that we can do cloud
computing at this point we've got AWS as
you're digitalocean Rackspace anything
using OpenStack how are these different
platforms going to evolve over time and
how should developers assess this
situation
that's it that's a really great question
right so you know what what we've seen
over the last few years is obviously a
great expansion in some of the market
leaders like Amazon and Microsoft Azure
we've seen the guys at Google do some
really great work they're starting to
turn their attention toward you know
enterprise which is which is new for
them and you know over time I think that
what we're gonna see is a couple of
things we will see
I think continued competition amongst
the big players right so the players
like that have you know cash in the bank
right and they they want to control you
know they want to build data centers
they want to be you know in the real
estate power cooling business and so
we'll see continued expansion you know
from Microsoft and Amazon and Apple and
and you know some of these other guys
the second thing that we're gonna see is
competition in the vertical cloud space
so I as a cloud service provider it's me
very difficult for me to really compete
in this highly competitive price
sensitive commodity business right but
if I bring value and I if I build a
cloud that is targeted at a particular
vertical whether it be government
oriented whether it be health care
oriented whatever allows me to provide
unique value for particular segments of
the market I think that we will start
seeing those verticals as well
ultimately you know I think that what
happens is is that all this
commoditization the API is over the top
of them in the Amazon API or or the
OpenStack API over Rackspace is cloud I
believe that is going to be subsumed
right so just like today when I put my
workload into a cloud I don't know where
it's running I think in the future I'll
be able to
put a work load into the cloud fabric
and the fabric will be able to through
heuristics algorithms the evaluation a
lot of data will be able to place the
workload into an Amazon data center or a
Microsoft data center or private data
center depending upon the business
policies that have been defined so I I
my personal view and this this is what
we're working on anatomic is to create
that world
mmm yeah that sounds really interesting
so do you think it'll be like so not - I
know we're up against time but not to
ask a big question but I'll just ask a
big question do you think it's going to
be like a polyglot cloud world where
like I'm I'm a big company and I've got
my media cloud that runs on maybe
Netflix data and and I've got my machine
learning running on Google Data Center
because Google is great it you know
Google's great at machine learning
platform as a service and maybe I've got
storage on Amazon because Amazon is the
is best at that are we going towards a
polyglot cloud world I I believe that
we're going towards that world and it'll
be driven by by business policies and by
the features and configuration of the
various clouds so that when I say I've
got this particular workload and it has
these characteristics maybe one of the
characteristics is machine learning
right the system will say oh I know that
this should go toward Google right
rather than Amazon or you know this is
my dev test environment find me the
cheapest place out there maybe it'll end
up it on a digital ocean server
someplace right so I I do believe that
that is where the world's going I'm very
excited about heuristic and algorithmic
automation I think it's really the third
leg on the stool right so so I think
that the three legs are traditional
automation that we have today
application release automation and data
center automation and that's been going
on on for several years right I started
as like runbook automation and workload
automation now we're doing a lot of
DevOps things anatomic plays in that
space the second leg is the cloud native
automation really coming out of the past
world right so you know if you take a
look at Cloud Foundry openshift Heroku
they have a really
ecosystem around the developer and there
they have opinionated automation right
for the operators right so I I see that
those two worlds are going to be coming
together sooner rather than later and
then of course the third leg is that
heuristic or algorithmic automation
where it's non-deterministic it's driven
by policies you basically tell you you
tell the system what you want and the
system is getting a load of data right
you know you know call it Internet of
Things from sensors telemetry data from
servers and networks and so on and so
forth and it is able to say hey for this
particular workload let's put it here
you know whether it be Google or let's
put it in the Cleveland Ohio private
data center that we have depending upon
the characteristics of the workload and
the availability of the resources
okay well that's a great place to close
off where can people find out more about
you John I would go to WWE Tommy calm
you know that's our website and I'm also
on Twitter at John / great okay well
we'll put both of those in the show
notes John thanks for coming onto
software engineering radio and giving up
some of your time to talk about
OpenStack this has been great I've had a
great time thanks for having me on
[Music]
thanks for listening to se radio an
educational program brought to you by I
Triple E software magazine for more
information about the podcast including
other episodes visit our web site at se
- radio - to provide feedback you can
write comments on each episode on the
website or write a review on iTunes
mention a message us on Twitter at se
radio or search for the software
engineering radio group on LinkedIn
Google+ or Facebook you can also email
us at team @ SC - radio net this and all
other episodes of se radio is licensed
under the creative commons
two-point-five license thanks again for
your support
[Music]